Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is קמ"ו עמוד ב',
kof mem vav amud bet, 146b, and we start with a משנה.
mishnah. And after a brief excursion into the world of שושבינות shushbinot
and סבלונות, sovlonot, which had which came to because of a question
about, you know, if they get reciprocated after the father dies, how
do they get, you know, to which of the brothers do they
go back. Really the discussions should have more been in like כתובות
Ketubot or maybe קידושין. Kiddushin. But anyway, we return back now to
the basic issue about inheriting, and we finally, finally, finally, the day
you've all been waiting for, come to the משנה mishnah that directly
discusses the idea, the transition, as it were, between, you know, we
had like death and inheritance in the תורה, Torah, reassigning the amount,
יוחנן בן ברוקה, Yochanan ben Broka, identifying the בכור bechor but still
working within the inheritance of the תורה, Torah, we had a gift,
and now we're finally getting to the מתנת שכיב מרע, matnat sh'chiv
mera, the deathbed bequest that the that we that is sort of
the Rabbinic institution to be able to play the role of a
will.
And so let's take a look at it. And the basic principle,
maybe I should start by saying two basic principles about this. One
basic principle is that דברי שכיב מרע ככתובים וכמסורים דמי, divrei sh'chiv
mera k'chtuvim u'chemesurim dami,
that the words are like you've handed over the property. דברי שכיב
מרע ככתובים וכמסורים דמי.
divrei sh'chiv mera k'chtuvim
u'chemesurim dami.
It's like they have been written, I guess, like a שטר shtar
and handed over if it was מטלטלין. metaltelin. So basically the words
create the קנין. kinyan. You do not need an act of a
קנין. kinyan. That's principle number one. Okay? That's the power of it.
That's the חידוש chiddush of it.
The other point of is that, you know, obviously it's all part
of the חידוש chiddush should be, you know, maybe it goes without
saying that it takes place at death. Okay. So, you know, the
implicit point number two, which is, you know, it takes place at
death. That what the גמרא's Gemara's discussion before takes place at the
moment of death. Before, you know, and the גמרא Gemara had this
question, was it עם גמר מיתה, im g'mar mita, you know, בשעת
מיתה, bi-sh'at mita,
whatever. We had different designations. But anyway, okay. But anyway, fine.
But anyway, there's a question of exactly when. But the real point
here is, let's just put that in parentheses, that's like implicit. But
the real other important point about the שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera is
is אם עמד חוזר. im amad chozer. Since the whole point was
that he thought he was about to die and he was doing
the deathbed bequest, that if he if he gets better, eventually of
course he will die, so will we all, sorry to disappoint you,
okay, but if he gets better from that illness, okay, and he
now is going around as a healthy guy, okay, now the question
the גמרא Gemara discusses of how recuperating is עמד, amad, but nevertheless
it automatically is voided, okay, because it was all given with the
assumption that he was going to die. Now that is different than
a דיאטיקי, dyatiki, right? A דיאטיקי dyatiki is like a written will,
which sort of works in a similar type of a context and
there we have like דיאטיקי מבטלת דיאטיקי, dyatiki mivatteles dyatiki, but you
know where like you can write a later will to override the
earlier one. But here the point to emphasize is and how does
דיאטיקי dyatiki fit into שכיב מרע, sh'chiv mera, whatever. But here the
point to emphasize is that as if he gets up, it automatically,
it's not just he has the right to revoke it, it automatically
is revoked. Now, that's those are the two major points, okay? But
there's a very important to distinguish also between two scenarios. One is
when he gives it all away, okay, כל נכסיו kol nechasav
and
מקצת נכסיו. miktzat nechasav. Now the difference between כל נכסיו kol nechasav
and מקצת נכסיו miktzat nechasav is that if he's dividing all of
his property, okay, the implication is that he's doing it because he
thinks he's going to die, okay, because he's dividing all of his
property, okay, so there, so in that type of a case,
a קנין kinyan unnecessary,
unnecessary, because he's on the deathbed.
He's on the deathbed.
Okay. If he's dividing all of his property, a קנין kinyan is
unnecessary, that's just rule. It's just his words. Words, words, words, words,
words, words. It's just his words. Anybody get the reference? Okay anyway.
But if it's part of his property, well if you really think
you're going to die, why are you only dividing part of your
property? Just divide, you know, divide it all. Of course the answer
could be, I want the rest to be inherited by my kids.
So that makes an interesting question. Let's say he says, you know,
this field to this, this field to this, this field to this,
and the rest should be inherited. Maybe that does count as כל
נכסיו. kol nechasav. But if it's מקצת נכסיו, miktzat nechasav, then the
fact that you're not doing it all means we're not seeing it
as a deathbed bequest, okay? We're not seeing it, you know, because
we're not seeing it like you're expecting to die and you're seeing
this as the way where you're, you know, bequeathing your property. So
this מקצת נכסיו miktzat nechasav is you need a קנין. kinyan. Okay,
because we don't have that rule that the words just work. קנין
Kinyan needed. Okay? However, okay, because of that, let's ask about the
other issue. Not about these are these two points, right? These are
שכיב מרע Shechiv Mera and עמד וחזר. Amad V'Chozer. So כל נכסיו
Kulyo Nechaso is the principle if עמד וחזר. Amad V'Chozer. Okay. מקצת
נכסיו, Mikzas Nechaso, what do you think it would be if he
recuperated? Any thoughts? Does it automatically void it or not?
No. Okay. עמד ואינו חוזר. Amad V'eino Chozer.
Okay,
because that's not seen as that's just seen as a קנין. Kinyan.
Okay, so the basic point is the principle, the rabbinic category of
שכיב מרע Shechiv Mera is just a קנין Kinyan you did on
your deathbed. Okay, it was very nice, guy's on his deathbed, fine,
and he did a קנין. Kinyan. So it just follows normal laws
of קניינים. Kinyanim. The institution of שכיב מרע, Shechiv Mera, right, is
when it's כל נכסיו. Kulyo Nechaso. That's when you don't need a
קנין Kinyan and that's when אם עמד חוזר. Im Amad Chozer. Yes?
Why would somebody do that? Either they say, oh, I forgot to
make a will and I'm going to die, or like I made
a will and you know, I don't like it and I didn't
get around to changing it, so now I'll change it.
Well, we're going to have to see about whether דייתיקי Dyatiki might
just work as a type of a written-out דברי שכיב מרע Divrei
Shechiv Mera and on your own also and then would be as
the reason and it sort of seemed like that earlier that it
doesn't have any more power than a written-out דברי שכיב מרע. Divrei
Shechiv Mera. Fact maybe has a little less power because by דברי
שכיב מרע Divrei Shechiv Mera you just say it, it's binding, whereas
if you write it out it might not be binding until you
actually hand it or well not binding until it's handed to the
next party. So it could be a דייתיקי Dyatiki is a subcategory
of דברי שכיב מרע. Divrei Shechiv Mera. So let's take a look
at the משנה. Mishnah. Okay? שכיב מרע שכתב כל נכסיו לאחרים. Shechiv
mera she-kasav kulyo nechasav l'acherim. He gives away, he divests all of
his property to others ושייר קרקע כל שהוא, V'shiyer karka kol shehu,
and he left over a little bit, okay, so this is now
מקצת נכסיו Mikzas Nechaso is better, so let's modify this to, like,
it's not like he leaves over ten dollars in the bank, okay,
and land is still seen as the primary definition of the property
and inheritance. So this is שייר קרקע כל שהוא. Shiyer karka kol
shehu. That's really the more accurate definition of מקצת נכסיו. Mikzas Nechaso.
ושייר קרקע כל שהוא מתנתו קיימת. V'shiyer karka kol shehu matanaso kayemes.
Okay, it is a valid מתנה Matanah and the point being of
course some of the keywords here are are
even if he gets better. Even if he's עמד, Amad, מתנתו קיימת,
Matanaso kayemes, it's still valid. אבל לא שייר קרקע כל שהוא, Aval
lo shiyer karka kol shehu, if he didn't leave over a little
bit, אין מתנתו קיימת, Ein matanaso kayemes, and then he gets better.
Right? That big important clause and he gets better is missing from
the משנה, Mishnah, anyway, so that's the way the גמרא Gemara reads
it. You could read it in a radically different way. You could
basically say like חז"ל Chazal only allowed to be institution if you
left over some property. That would be strange. Okay, so anyway the
גמרא's Gemara reading it as that we're talking about this עמד Amad
aspect. המידי דקנין? Hamidi d'kinyan?
But it does not discuss the קנין Kinyan issue yet. Yes, Charlie?
Wasn't there a case a couple of weeks ago where we were
talking about giving,
redirecting
your inheritance, where there was an idea that you should at least
have a small part of your estate that is divided according to?
Yes. Yes. So the כלל Klal that's important, right, that's a good
point, meaning once the גמרא Gemara sort of says like you shouldn't
completely disinherit your kids or like completely give away everything so then
you never have a כל נכסיו Kulyo Nechaso case. We're going to
see like in a day or two the definition of כל נכסיו.
Kulyo Nechaso. Okay. And maybe, you know, explicitly saying like and the
rest is for my kids, right? But you don't, you know, that
might include be included. So anyway let's take a look at the
גמרא, Gemara, yes.
So in effect if the person's aware of this, these conditions then
he's really he's giving it all away knowing that he's going to
get it back if he doesn't pass on to the next world.
You know what I'm saying?
When he שייר קרקע כל שהוא? Shiyer karka kol shehu?
Yeah, when he gives it all away
except for a little piece of land.
Yes, all of his estate.
Oh, all of it.
Yeah, all of it. So I mean he knows that, you know,
he's giving it all away but it's because he thinks he's going
to die but he knows also that if he doesn't die he's
going to get it all back.
Right. So that's a very it's very safe to operate that way.
Right. Exactly. Exactly. And that's why this, you know, in this context
here they wanted to like give you the security that you could
basically divest your you know write out your will or speak out
your will and not be afraid that like it's you know and
and ensure that it's only going to be effective, right, if and
when you die. Okay.
So we say שכתב, Shekasav, it doesn't mean שכתב Shekasav really. We're
saying that he physically somehow.
Yeah, you don't really it's true, right. If you look at the
first lines of the רשב"ם, Rashbam, והוא הדין חילק על פיו בלא
כתיבה. V'hu hadin chilek al piv belo kesivah. Right. So but the
point here is the שכתב, Shekasav, right, because we're talking about the
שייר קרקע כל שהוא, Shiyer karka kol shehu, it does need to
be some קנין, Kinyan, right? The משנה Mishnah says שייר קרקע כל
שהוא Shiyer karka kol shehu then it's valid and we're reading even
if he gets better it's valid. But it needs to be some
קנין. Kinyan. So either it's כתב Kasav or it would be a
קנין סודר Kinyan sudar or something. So the כתב Kasav is doing
an important thing in here, some act of a קנין Kinyan is
needed. Okay. All right. So now let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. So it says like this. Oh by the way we might
as well look at. So let's take a look at the רשב"ם
Rashbam where it says מתני', Masnis, two lines below that, where he
just has an important definition of how do you frame it as
מתנת שכיב מרע. Mattnas Shchiv Me-ra. Is it anything he says when
he's lying, when he's in his sickbed? How do you know if
it's a sickbed or a deathbed? Okay, so if you go down
one line under where it says מתני' Masnis at the end of
the line, he says like this: וכגון שהיו עדים שהיה שכיב מרע.
U’ch’gon she-hayu edim she-haya shchiv me-ra. First of all, we have to
have evidence that he was a שכיב מרע, shchiv me-ra, with some
definition of like that we know he was in what, you know,
he believed to be his deathbed. Okay, כשכתב או נתן מתנה זו,
k’she-katav o natan matana zu, when he either when he was given
it. So number one, either we know as a fact, established fact,
he was like, you know, people thought he was like critically ill.
או, O, or even if we haven't had as an established fact,
we don't have witnesses or maybe it even wasn't true. But what
if somebody when they're well, when they're nice and healthy, you know,
wants to plan ahead and write a will? They don't want to
wait until the last minute. Can you use this instrument? So you
can by claiming in the שטר shtar that you said it when
you were in the deathbed, right? Well, the problem is that no,
probably it wouldn't work actually. I shouldn't have gone that far because
since אם עמד חוזר, im amad chozer,
then if you're seen walking around healthy after the שטר shtar was
written, it would be a state of אם עמד חוזר. im amad
chozer. So anyway, so we'll have to see about that. But anyway,
here's what he says. Either witnesses, you know, can testify that the
guy was in his
deathbed או שכתב בשטר o she-katav ba-shtar or the שטר, shtar, in
the שטר shtar it's written כד קציר. k’ad katzir. קציר Katzir is
the Aramaic word for sick. Okay, when somebody is sick, כד קציר,
k’ad katzir, when he was sick ורמי בערסיה u’rami b’arsye and lying
in bed, you know, he directed, he said the following statement. Okay,
so the שטר shtar says either the שטר shtar itself says this
was said when I was like lying in bed and you know
in my sickbed and because, well, in that time in particular also
if you're sick for more than you know for a few days,
likely you might die, right? Because they didn't know how to treat,
you know, illness the same way. Okay, so either the שטר shtar
says it or witnesses testify. So that's how do you know it's
in this context for שכיב מרע. shchiv me-ra. That's either what's written
in the שטר shtar or what witnesses are saying.
So literally שכיב מרע shchiv me-ra means like a bad sleep or
a bad bed.
Right, like lying down because of illness, because of in a bad
state. Yeah, exactly. That's a good point. That's exactly what the word
means. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. מאן תנא דאזלינן בתר אומדנא.
Man tana d’azlinan batar umdana.
Now, the fact that אם עמד חוזר im amad chozer when it's
call all of it is based on, now you could just say
this is all just a rabbinic institution, take it or leave it.
We just set in the rules and if you want to use
this, here's how it works. But the גמרא Gemara understands that it
works on the principle of, the real חידוש chiddush of the rabbinic
institution is קניין kinyan is unnecessary. The idea that if he gets
better it's all voided, that we didn't wasn't part of like what
the rabbis said. That's just a normal application of the rules, which
is that obviously he was giving this because he thought he was
about to die. And if he's, so he never wanted it to
be binding if he actually got better. Okay, so that's the principle
of אזלינן בתר אומדנא, azlinan batar umdana, we go based on assessing
his state of mind. Okay, so who's that תנא tana that says
that? אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, says Rav Nachman, רבי שמעון
בן מנסיא היא, Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya hee, it's Rabbi Shimon ben
Menasya, we've seen this before. דתניא, D’tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא,
braita, הרי שהלך בנו למדינת הים ושמע שמת בנו. Harei she-halach b’no
l’medinat ha-yam v’shama she-met b’no. So his son went away overseas to
England and then he heard that his son died. ואמר וכתב כל
נכסיו לאחרים, V’amar v’chatav kol nechasav l’acherim, and so he got up
and he gifted all his property to somebody else. Now he didn't
say, oh my God my son is dead here take all my
property. Okay, it's just the sequence of events. You know, on Monday
he heard his son died, on Tuesday he granted all his property
to somebody else.
Is this like four years later?
Well, right, that's always the question. Exactly how do you define exactly
the right context. Okay, ואחר כך בא בנו, v’achar kach ba b’no,
and then his son showed up, ברוך השם. Baruch Hashem. מתנתו מתנה,
Matnaso matana, it's still valid. That would be the principle of דברים
שבלב אינם דברים. d’varim she-ba-lev einam d’varim. Okay, we don't care, it
wasn't an explicit condition, it's still valid. That's the תנא קמא. Tana
Kama. רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya omer, Rabbi
Shimon ben Menasya says, אין מתנתו מתנה, ein matnaso matana, it's not
valid, שאילו היה יודע שבנו קיים, she-ilu haya yodei she-b’no kayam, were
he to know that his son were alive, לא היה כותבן, lo
haya kosvan, he would never have written it. Okay, so we go
by his state of mind. So that's one תנא tana that says
you go by his state of mind. And that's like, you know.
Okay, and רב ששת אמר, Rav Sheshet amar, Rav Sheshet says, רבי
שמעון שזורי היא, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri hee, it's Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. דתניא,
D’tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא, braita, בראשונה היו אומרים, Berishona hayu
omrim, originally they said, היוצא בקולר, hayotzei b’kolar, somebody taken out in
chains about to be executed by the government, the Roman government, ואמר
כתבו גט לאשתי, v’amar kitvu get l’ishti, write a גט get for
my wife. Although if anybody learned גיטין, Gittin, he's missing one verb.
What should he say? כתבו ותנו גט לאשתי. Kitvu u’snu get l’ishti.
Because somebody could say write a גט get for my wife so
I'll have it in my back pocket when I need it. Okay,
but in this context, of course he means give it, he's afraid
he's about to be executed but he didn't say it. Okay, הרי
אלו יכתבו ויתנו, harei elu yichtevu v’yitnu, so you can write it
and give it. חזרו לומר, Chazru lomar, then they expanded this category,
when do we read the word כתבו kitvu to mean כתבו ותנו?
kitvu u’snu? אף המפרש והיוצא בשיירה, Af ha-mefaresh v’ha-yotzei bi-sh’yara,
even somebody going on an overseas journey or going on a caravan.
tumult, right,
that he can't, that he's
not thinking straight to exactly say the full legal phrase that he'd
like to say it. Okay, רבי
שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri says אף המסוכן, Af Hamisukan,
even somebody who is in like, you know, deathly ill, is in
danger of dying. That's what מסוכן misukan means in this context. That's
exactly like a שכיב מרע. shachiv meira. Okay, now תוספות Tosafos says,
by the way, that really it's not just רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri, everybody in this משנה, mishna, even the first part of
it, understood אזלינן בתר אומדנא. ozlinan basar umdana. You read the word
into the word כתבו kisvu also the word תנו. tnu. But רבי
שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri is just as, is more prepared to
do it, right? He would do it even in a wider variety
of cases, but they all pretty much agree to the principle. All
right, so it's one of those approaches that says you get into
the guy's head. Now, as I said before and I'll say it
again, you know, the question is how does this work with the
principle of דברים שבלב אינם דברים? devarim shebelev einam devarim? That for
things to be legally meaningful in transactions, they have to be explicitly
stated. So look at this tiny little תוספות, Tosafos, okay, מן טעמא
דאזיל בתר אומדנא, Man ta'ama d'ozil basar umdana, so תוספות Tosafos says
צריך עיון לשבחה החמירותא בדברים שבלב אינם דברים. Tzarich iyun l'shavecha hachamirosa
b'devarim shebelev einam devarim. There is, I don't know,
we have to figure out how this idea fits with the principle
that everything has to be said explicitly. Okay,
ובפרק השני דקידושין הארכתי בהן, U'v'perek hasheini d'Kiddushin ha'arachti bahen, go look
there where I had a long discussion. The basic, the best answer
to this question תוספות Tosafos in קידושין Kiddushin tries to sort of
say, well, it depends how evident it is. If it's evident to
everybody, it doesn't have to be stated. If it's not so evident,
it has to be stated. The best answer is what רמב"ם Rambam
and the תוספות רי"ד Tosafos Rid say. And they say that this
is true of אזלינן בתר אומדנא ozlinan basar umdana in cases of
one-sided transactions, like a מתנה matana or a what was the other
case we had here? We had a מתנה matana and a גט.
get. Both of those you don't need the agreement of the other
side. Well, מתנה matana you sort of need the agreement of the
other side, but they're not like but you know but they're basically
just receiving. Okay, in a מתנה matana they're not giving up something
of their own that you really need to make sure that everything
is spelled out for the other side. So there where it's not
really about the other side, right, so maybe we really do try
to assess the person's frame of mind. And if he didn't have
full דעת, da'as, it won't be binding. Whereas if it's a two-sided
transaction, obviously the law will say the other you cannot make the
other person responsible for guessing what's in your head. Okay, and that's
why דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebelev einam devarim. So it's actually
very nice, the רמב"ם Rambam in the beginning of
like הלכות מכירה Hilchos Mechira basically says, I forget the exact language
but he basically says when somebody sells something, whatever and in case
or wherever מקח וממכר, mekach u'mimkar, דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim shebelev
einam devarim, and in הלכות זכיה ומתנה Hilchos Zechiya U'Matana he says
לעולם אומדין l'olam omdin with an א, aleph, you always assess דעת
הנותן, da'as hanosein, the דעת da'as of the one who's given, not
who sells, who's giving, right? Anyway, so that's like, so that's, so
that all works here because all of these are basically one-sided gifts.
Yes. Rabbi, could you just repeat that? Yeah,
that if it's a gift and it's one-sided, if it's a gift
or a גט, get, you don't really, the other side doesn't really
have to agree to anything. You know, a gift he has to
accept it, but nevertheless, without, you know, so therefore we can try
to assess was that your intent or not your intent. But if
it's a two-sided transaction, even if it wasn't fully your intent, but
you the other side can't be bound by something that you're not
making explicit. So דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebelev einam devarim. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara wraps this up and says like this.
רב נחמן מאי טעמא לא מוקי לה כרבי שמעון שזורי? Rav Nachman
mai ta'ama lo moki lah k'Rabbi Shimon Shezuri? So okay, both of
these seem good טענות. ta'anos. Why did one take one and one
take the other? So why did רב נחמן Rav Nachman not use
רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri of a גט get to be
the evidence that you go by אומדנא? umdana? So שאני התם דאמר
כתבו. shani hasam d'amar kisvu. Yeah, that's that's true. There you're not
basically set using his דעת da'as to negate what he did, right,
like he gives a gift and then his דעת da'as was we're
voiding the gift. That was in the case of the שכיב מרע
shachiv meira and the son who he heard had died. The case
of the guy with the גט, get, it's a much easier case.
He said כתבו kisvu and you're using his דעת da'as to fill
in the extra word, not to negate what he's saying, but just
to fill in the sentence. Okay, or even to say the word
כתבו kisvu in this context means כתבו ותנו. kisvu u'tnu. All right.
רב ששת מאי, Rav Sheshes mai, so that's really a good answer.
רב ששת מאי טעמא לא מוקי לה כרבי שמעון בן מנסיא? Rav
Sheshes mai ta'ama lo moki lah k'Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya? So why
did רב ששת Rav Sheshes not go like רבי שמעון בן מנסיא,
Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya, which is much more parallel? Why did he
get this case of גט get to be the evidence? אומדנא דמוכח
שאני, Umdana d'mokeach shani, which is sort of what I told you
תוספות' Tosafos' approach to reconciling these various things. He said, no, in
the case where the son had just died, that's like self-evident. Okay,
in these other cases they're not self-evident as self-evident. So he wanted
a case where the where the frame of mind was not as
self-evident. I know, I think it's, well, מסוכן misukan maybe is not
as self-evident. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, מן
תנא להא דתנו רבנן? man tana l'ha d'tanu rabanan? Who is the
תנא tana of that which we taught in this following תוספתא? Tosefta?
הרי שהיה חולה ומוטל במטה, Harei shehaya choleh u'mutal b'mitah,
so somebody was sick and he was, you know, and he was
lying in bed, okay, ואמרו לו נכסיך למי, v'amru lo nechasyecha l'mi,
who your property to who? your property go to. ואומר, ve'omer, right,
this is a perfect example of דברי שכיב מרע, divrei shechiv mera,
right? So they actually in some sense, you know, the people have
to initiate, like the person himself may not be thinking about that.
ואומר להם, ve'omer lahem, סבור הייתי שיש לי בן. savur hayiti sheyesh
li ben. You know, I always thought that I had a son,
but I don't know, I heard reports at some, you know, whatever,
that the wife I had, you know, who knows, wife I left
in China 30 years ago, gave birth. Okay, עכשיו שאין לי בן,
achshav she'ein li ben, now it seems I don't have a son,
because you know whatever, he never showed up or anything. Okay, so
נכסיי לפלוני. nichasai le-Ploni. So let it all go to Reuven. Okay,
now, היה חולה. hayah choleh. Now here's another scenario. מוטל במיטה mutal
be-mitah ואמרו לו, ve-amru lo, נכסיך למי. nichasecha le-mi. He's sick and
he's and he said who do we give who should he give
his property. אמר להם, amar lahem, סבור הייתי שאשתי מעוברת. savur hayiti
she-ishti me'uberet. You know, I thought my wife was pregnant, okay, and
then it wouldn't have been a problem because then obviously the child
would have inherited. עכשיו שאין אשתי מעוברת, achshav she-ein ishti me'uberet, now
it seems that she's not pregnant because whatever now I heard differently,
okay, maybe I heard she miscarried, whatever it was. So in that
case, נכסיי לפלוני. nichasai le-Ploni. Too bad, he would have maybe just
said נכסיי לאשתי, nichasai le-ishti, but anyway, okay, let it go to
somebody else. Alright, let it go to this person. So those are
cases where he makes statements which it's clearly revealing his state of
mind. And it turns out that his assumptions were incorrect. ונודע שיש
לו בן או שהיתה אשתו מעוברת. ve-noda she-yesh lo ben o she-haytah
ishto me'uberet. It actually his first assumption was right and his second
one wasn't. His wife was still pregnant, he really did have a
child.
So אם מתנתו מתנה, im matnato matanah, so therefore the gift is
voided. So that seems to be the same idea. You go by
אומדנא דעתא. umdena da'ata. So the גמרא Gemara says, right, that's the
state of mind that we're assessing. לימא רבי שמעון בן מנסיא היא.
leima Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya hi. Let's say this is Rabbi Shimon
ben Menasya. Notice the גמרא Gemara does not say רבי שמעון שזורי.
Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya is
the much better parallel. It's a gift and then your דעת da'at
is voiding the gift. Okay, anyway, so let's say it's Rabbi Shimon
ben Menasya ולא רבנן, ve-lo rabbanan, not the Rabbis? No, אפילו תימא
רבנן, afillu teima rabbanan, even the Rabbis who argue in the case
of I heard my the guy who heard his son was dead
and he gifted his property, etc. דומא שאני. domya shani.
In that case, I remember I said to you, Monday he heard
his son died, Tuesday he gifted his property. So then we could
debate, right, what was his frame of mind or not a frame
of mind? Do we go by his frame of mind when he
doesn't say anything, etc.? Here the guy, A, there's no question that
that was his frame of mind because he said, oh, now I
realize I don't have a son. Okay, and not only do we
know his frame of mind, he actually said it! So it's no
longer like דברים שבלב, devarim she-ba-lev, right? He actually articulated that that
was the framing of the gift. Okay, so that's such a good
answer. Like, what, right? So that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
דקארי לה מאי קארי לה? de-ka'ari lah mai ka'ari lah? Which part
of it is better, that he said it out loud?
He said it out, well that's, yes, he said it out loud.
So but he said it out loud accomplishes two things. Number one
is it lets us know for sure that it was his frame
of mind as opposed to just guessing whether it was his frame
of mind. And number two, it could be that it's almost explicitly
stating, I only want this to be a gift given the circumstances
that X, Y, and Z. So it's like it's not even דברים
שבלב devarim she-ba-lev anymore. So the גמרא Gemara says, דקארי לה מאי
קארי לה? de-ka'ari lah mai ka'ari lah? So what was what were
you thinking when you asked the question? I mean, he he said
it explicitly here. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, מהו דתימא שרי
הוא דקא מדכר. mahu de-teima shari hu de-ka madkar. Maybe he doesn't
mean that that should be in the contextualized for gift. Maybe he
just means like, oy, you know, you talk to me about my
ירושה, yerusha, like I didn't even leave over any heirs, I feel
so whatever, and then he's giving something. So he means so he's
like he's, you know, he's talking about his feeling, but he doesn't
mean it to contextualize, you know, the circumstance of the gift. Of
course, even that, pretty clear that that therefore would be his state
of mind. Okay, but it would not necessarily be if you really
required like, you know, things to be explicit, then it might then
you might need it to be clear not just that this is
how you're feeling but that you want the act to be to
be only in the context if this is actually true. Okay, so
קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that we don't say that, that
we actually read those words to contextualize the gift. Okay, אמר רבי
דקארי לה
מאי קארי לה
amar
Rabbi de-ka'ari
lah mai ka'ari lah means you're just saying what?
No, no, no, no, no. דקארי לה מאי קארי לה de-ka'ari lah
mai ka'ari lah is the way the גמרא Gemara says what was
occurring to you? Occurring like קרי kari occurring? I don't know where
he got it from, but no, מאי קארי mai kari from some
קרה.
karah. Not קרה, karah, but this is what happened to him.
Yeah, this is what went over. That's what I mean, not קרה,
koreh, קרי? keri? Right, like no, but not him. It's a general
phrase in the גמרא Gemara where the גמרא Gemara says you who
thought the A, hey, which תנא tanna is it? Whatever. What type
of stupid question was that? Of course this is going according to
everybody. Of course this is a different case. What were you thinking
when you asked that question? Okay, to go it's a way it's
a good point of pedagogy, Rabbi Dove. If somebody asks for a
question, you should just say to them, what a stupid question! What
were you thinking? Because actually the גמרא Gemara first answers the question
and then it says, what were you thinking?
To make the person feel better once there's a result.
Right, right, exactly. But no, what it's really saying is explain to
me why this was a question you know, if you want to
say it nice. Explain what was, you know, why was this a
question? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: אמר amar רב זירא אמר רב *Amar Rav Zeira Amar Rav*.
Said what? Finally they're dealing with it.
Yeah, that's what I said before you came in, like finally, finally
we're directly dealing with that institution. אמר רב זירא אמר רב: מניין
למתנת שכיב מרע shechiv mera. מן התורה *Amar Rav Zeira Amar Rav:
Minayin lematnat shechiv mera min hatorah*? Where do you know it's from
the תורה *Torah*? So this we've been calling it a rabbinic institution,
here it's gonna seem to be shown that it's a biblical one.
Let's take a look.
שנאמר *Shene'emar*: והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו veha'avartem et nachalato l'vito. *Ve'avartem et
nachalato levitto*. You shall... this is, you know, if he doesn't have
any sons, you shall pass it over to the daughter. יש לך
העברה אחרת שכזו *Yesh lecha ha'avarah acheret shekazo*, you have another one
where you actively pass over your property. ואיזו זו? מתנת שכיב מרע
matnas shechiv mera *Ve'eizo zo? Matnat shechiv mera*. Now what exactly is
the דרשה *drashah*? רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* said either it's because it says
והעברתם v'ha'avartem, *ve'avartem* rather than ונתתם *unetatem*, but actually the next גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is gonna sort of read it from the word ונתתם
*unetatem*, so he seems to say because it didn't really need a
verb, it could have just said, ואם אין לו בן נחלתו לבתו
*Ve'im ein lo ben nachalato levitto*. Okay, so the fact that he
uses a verb, והעברתם *ve'avartem*, which makes the person an active role,
and in an inheritance the person isn't actively doing anything, right, he's
just dying and then the property goes over, so because it's framing
him with this active verb, okay, so therefore, you know, we should
see it that there are times when he can actively give a
מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shechiv mera *matnat shechiv mera*. Of course, the
point is that the והעברתם *ve'avartem* and ונתתם *unetatem* is that referring
to the person who died, it's referring to the community because it
says: איש כי ימות ובן אין לו *Ish ki yamut uven ein
lo*, it's in the singular. והעברתם *Ve'avartem*, you, the community, shall... but
what can I say, it's
called העברה *ha'avarah* because it's now going to the בת *bat*.
I understand, so he says it's half a דיוק *diyuk* on the
word העברה *ha'avarah*. It's the fact that it could have just said
נחלתו לבתו *nachalato levitto* and it uses a verb. ואיזו זו? מתנת
שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera, *Ve'eizo zo? Matnat shechiv mera*. What?
I don't know what that has to do with anything.
I understand, that's for חז"ל Hazal *Chazal* to read into it. But
it hints to you that there's ways in which a person could
be more active in his, you know, bequeathing his property. רב נחמן
Rav Nachman, אמר רבה בר אבוה מהכא *Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah bar
Avuha meihacha*: ונתתם את נחלתו לאחיו *Unetatem et nachalato le'achiv*. לאחיו *Le'achiv*.
לאחיו *Le'achiv*. I think it is. Anyway, and if he doesn't have
a daughter you give it to his brothers. יש לך נתינה אחרת
שכזו *Yesh lecha netinah acheret shekazo*. ואיזו זו? מתנת שכיב מרע matnat
shchiv mera, *Ve'eizo zo? Matnat shechiv mera*. Okay, now Michael's right, it
doesn't tell you where it is, that's for חז"ל *Chazal* to read
in, but at least it's indicating we're gonna see that there's a
way in which a person can be more active. ורב נחמן מאי
טעמא לא אמר מוהעברתם *Verav Nachman mai ta'ama lo amar meive'avartem*? Why
didn't he do the והעברתם *ve'avartem*? ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדרבי *Hahu mibayei
lei lechidrebi*, no, the use of the word והעברתם *ve'avartem* is not
to tell you this principle of מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera
*matnat shechiv mera*, but to tell you the דרשה *drashah* of רבי
*Rebi*. We've seen this before. דתניא *Detanya*, we learned in a brayta:
רבי אומר *Rebi omer*, בכולן נאמר בהן נתינה *bechulan ne'emar bahen netinah*,
in all the other times when it speaks about who gets the
inheritance it says you shall give it, וכאן *vecha'an*, and here when
there's only daughters, נאמר העברה *ne'emar ha'avarah*, it says right, I understand,
it says the word העברה *ha'avarah*, to pass over, to pass on
actually, you know, אין לך שמעביר נחלה משבט לשבט אלא בת *ein
lecha shema'avir nachalah mishevet leshevet ela bat*, because when you give it
to a בת *daughter*, you are diverting it, okay, you're diverting it
to the next tribe. She's gonna get married, if she gets married
and probably 99 percent of the marriages were within the tribe, but
if she gets married to a man of another tribe, then her
husband or her son will inherit her and the property will be
diverted. So that's the word והעברתם *ve'avartem*. ולבנה ולבעלה יורשין אותה *Ulevnah
uleva'alah yorshin otah*, since her husband and her son and her husband
inherit her. רב זירא מאי טעמא לא אמר מוונתתם *Rav Zeira mai
ta'ama lo amar mi'unetatem*? So why did Rav Zeira not use the
ונתתם *unetatem*? That's the signal of this מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv
mera, *matnat shechiv mera*? אורחא דקרא הוא *Orcha dikra hu*, that's just
the way of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, meaning ונתתם *unetatem* is not
an interesting verb. והעברתם *Ve'avartem* is an interesting verb.
Right, it's just like what I was trying to say.
We're not done. רב מנשיא בר ירמיה אמר מהכא *Rav Menashya bar
Yirmeya amar meihacha*: Rav Menashya bar Yirmeya says from the following. Okay.
So now Michael was pointing us to narratives as opposed to the
legal sections of the תורה *Torah*. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is gonna do. It's gonna look at narratives. It's gonna even
go beyond the תורה *Torah*, which we normally don't look in נ"ך
*Nach* for legal rules. Let's take a look. Okay, but you could
sort of say גילוי מילתא *gilluy milta*, it's reflecting the reality of
this institution. So here are some of the interesting deathbed narratives in
תנ"ך *Tanach*. בימים ההם חלה חזקיהו למות *Bayamim haheim chalah Chizkiyahu lamut*,
in those days Chizkiyahu was ill and he was going to die,
ויבוא אליו ישעיהו בן אמוץ *vayavo eilav Yeshayahu ben Amot*, and the
נביא *navi* Yeshayahu came to him, ויאמר אליו *vayomer eilav*, כה אמר
ה' *ko amar Hashem*: צו לביתך כי מת אתה *tzav leveitecha ki
met atah*, command your household because you will die, ולא תחיה *velo
tichyeh*, and you won't live. And then in the end whatever, there's
a whole story then he does תשובה *teshuvah*, whatever, he turns to
the wall, he cries. Anyway, not for us. Anyway, בצוואה בעלמא *betzava'ah
be'alma*, but you see when he says take care of your household
issues, of your household affairs before you die, he says give the
command, command your household, which seems like just the verbal command, verbal
expression of what he wants to be done with his household becomes
binding. בצוואה בעלמא *Betzava'ah be'alma*. It actually does sound like that. Okay.
Now again, that doesn't prove that it's legally binding. It could just
mean, you know, societally they would have followed through with what the
person said.
Or as the king would do it, but nobody else...
or as the king maybe. Okay. But... Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says well we're going to have a non-king case. רמי בר יחזקאל
אמרי הכא Rami bar Yehezkel amrei hacha says from here, ואחיתפל
ראה כי לא נעשתה עצתו Va'Achitofel ra'ah ki lo na'astah atzato that
his counsel, thank you, was not
followed, ויחבש את החמור וילך אל ביתו אל עירו ויצו אל ביתו
ויחנק. vayachavosh et hachamor vayelech el beito el iro vayetzav el beito
vayechaneik. So he
and he commanded for his household to divest the property, that's what
it's saying, he took care of his affairs, right? Go take care
of your affairs. And then he basically he strangled, he committed suicide,
right? He killed himself, right? He strangled himself. בצוואה דעלמא. Betzava d'alma.
So you see just by the verbal command. All right, so therefore
those are the evidence. Now, he did commit suicide? Yeah. Well, that's
a good point, meaning these are persons that were not, this case
he was not on a deathbed, he was anticipating his death because
he was about to commit suicide, but he wasn't on a deathbed.
That's a good point.
Right, and then if it also a temporary הלכה, halakha, if somebody
commits suicide is there a, his
wishes are, yeah, the wishes are fulfilled, meaning there's a נפקא מינה
nafkamina like the suicide issue obviously, we talk about like did they
get buried in a normal with a plot or whatever, but the
technical issues here would not be the sort of the moral wrongness
of suicide, the sin of suicide, it would be the question of
did they create that institution only when a guy was on a
deathbed, or on a guy who was anticipating death even though he
wasn't on his deathbed? Right, let's say a person is about to
go into a flaming building to try to save an infant and
it's clear he's afraid he might not come out, right, and he
gives a צוואה, tzava, is that a דברי שכיב מרע? divrei shchiv
mera? It's a really good question. Right? You're anticipating your possible or
your almost definite death, okay? And somebody's going on a suicide mission
to save somebody, and
does, would that be included in דברי שכיב מרע? divrei shchiv mera?
That's a really good question. I'd have to look into that. Okay,
so now anyway, so those are the issues. Now, does the גמרא
Gemara really mean it's דאורייתא? d'Oraita? It sounds like it and the
גמרא Gemara later is going to contrast it to אמוראים Amoraim who
say that it's דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. Okay, but with that being said, take
a look at the תוספות. Tosafot. מנין למתנת שכיב מרע שהוא מן
התורה? Minayin l'matnat shchiv mera shehu min haTorah? תוספות Tosafot says, לא
מן התורה דוקא, lav min haTorah davka, you don't really mean that.
כמה דאמרת, k'ma d'amrat, now what's his evidence? דהא רב נחמן, deha
Rav Nachman, well first of all, there's not, it's not strong פסוקים
psukim to support that, but number two, that the first person to
give a פסוק that it's דאורייתא d'Oraita is רב נחמן, Rav Nachman
והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו. דרב נחמן גופיה איתא לקמן, DeRav Nachman gufei
isai d'kaman, רב נחמן Rav Nachman: is going to say when we
get to עמוד ב', amud bet, דינא כשל תורה ועשו כשל תורה.
deina k'shel Torah ve'asu k'shel Torah. It's not biblical, they just made
it as if it were biblical. אלא אסמכתא הוא דקאמר. Ela asmachta
hu d'kamar. Okay? So we're just saying that it's an אסמכתא. asmachta.
האי, Hai, well how do you make it like it's biblical? Which
is very interesting because that's not what the גמרא Gemara is saying
and it's going to contrast it to the approach that it's דרבנן.
d'Rabbanan. But the way תוספות Tosafot reads it is if we wanted
to frame it as if it were biblical, how would we be
packaging it as if it were biblical? As opposed to, as opposed
to just packaging it explicitly as דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, which by the way
makes the point that
Talmud scholars have made that the whole distinction between דאורייתא d'Oraita and
דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, the way we sort of have to clearly categorize everything,
wait, is this דאורייתא d'Oraita or דרבנן? d'Rabbanan? Here are the נפקא
מינות, nafkaminas, etc. Right? That was like a later part of the
process, because if the Rabbis are both interpreters and legislators, right? So
it's not always exactly clear, and it's all a function of rabbinic
activity, but obviously very different types of rabbinic activity. So like certainly
like in the time of the משנה Mishnah and the תנאים Tannaim
the difference between דאורייתא d'Oraita was, it wasn't like, obviously it wasn't
crystallized at all, but it was not like systematic and fully crystallized.
And even in the time of the גמרא Gemara there are things
that are left vague. So for example, רמב"ם Rambam says that you
transgress the prohibition, of בל תוסיף, Bal Tosif, if you claim that
something that's a דרבנן d'Rabbanan is a דאורייתא. d'Oraita. And you transgress
the prohibition of בל תגרע Bal Tigra if you claim that something
that's a דאורייתא d'Oraita is only a דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. So ראב"ד Ra'avad
says how can you say such a thing? There are many things
in the גמרא Gemara where it sounds like it's a דאורייתא d'Oraita
but it's really a דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. So what, like חז"ל were always
being עובר over on בל תוסיף? Bal Tosif? You know, the גמרא
Gemara itself is very vague sometimes about what exact category, and it
calls it a דאורייתא d'Oraita and it's just an אסמכתא asmachta and
so on. So why isn't the גמרא Gemara being עובר over on
בל תוסיף? Bal Tosif? So anyway, the point being is that sometimes,
yeah, there is this ambiguity and here's one of those cases. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנו רבנן, Tnu
rabanan, a little, a little digression here.
My answer to that is because what, the Rabbis themselves are deciding
what's דאורייתא? d'Oraita?
Well, yeah, maybe it hasn't always been fully, fully, either they knew
and they weren't always telling us, okay, which would really make it
a problem for רמב"ם's Rambam idea that you're misrepresenting and it's בל
תוסיף, Bal Tosif, or these things weren't all fully crystallized, you know?
Okay, תנו רבנן, Tnu rabanan, שלשה דברים צוה אחיתופל את בניו. shlosha
dvorim tziva Achitofel et banav. So this is just a total like
tradition we have, we're not going to read this into the פסוקים.
psukim. Three things he commanded his kids before he died. Number one,
אל תהיו במחלוקת. al tehyu bemachloket. Okay, taking a little advice from,
here he was, like he was part of this whole like plot
and it all failed. ואל תמרדו במלכות. Ve'al timr'du bemalkhut. Two very
things that clearly that's part of what happened, what, part of the
lesson he just learned. מלכות בית דוד. Malchus beit David. Oh. Other
kings, kingships you can rebel against, not מלכות בית דוד. Malchus beit
David. And number three, the יום טוב של עצרת, Yom Tov shel
Atzeres, the ברור barur
and in its the day of שבועות Shavuos is a clear day,
זרו חיטים, zaru chitim, plant wheat. How the גמרא Gemara decided that
this was the saying that he was telling his kids, but by
the way, the point so being and this is important, right? This
is reading into ויצו אל ביתו, Vayitzav el beito, which until now
we've been reading as a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera and
about giving, about מתנת שכיב מרע shchiv mera and about giving of,
you know, about the divesting of property. The גמרא Gemara is now
translating it as an ethical will, right, not a, not about my
property, nothing that's legally binding, right, but like here are the things
that I want to give you, my advice before I die, right?
I mean I think we've often lost the, you know, practice of
writing these like ethical wills which have been very powerful throughout
history. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now it's
going to go on this digression about planting wheat on a clear
day if שבועות Shavuos is clear. מר זוטרא Mar Zutra אמר בהיל.
bahil. No, no, no. One said if it's a clear day, the
other said if it was a cloudy day. Okay, so now that
totally throws the whole thing into question.
איתמר Itmar אמרי נהרדעי amrei Neharde'ei says משמיה דרבי יעקב, mishmeih de'Rabbi
Yaakov, לא ברור ברור ממש lo barur barur mamash ולא בהיל בהיל
ממש. velo bahil bahil mamash. No, no, no, it's not just a
totally clear day and it's not a cloudy day. אלא אפילו בהיל
ורוח צפונית מנשבת בו, ela afilu bahil ve'ruach tzafonis menasheves bo, זהו
ברור. zehu barur. Presumably understood that if it was a clear day
that's a good sign and you should plant wheat right away, but
he said a clear day includes a cloudy day but there's a
northern wind so it's scattering the clouds, that's also included. But wait
wait wait, can I ask a question?
Yeah. You're allowed to plant on שבועות? Shavuos?
Not on שבועות. Shavuos. If you see, if you see, thank you
for saying that, I mean I was being careful how I said
it, that if שבועות Shavuos is clear then you should begin to
plant wheat, but no, you plant after שבועות. Shavuos. But on the
day, it's like Groundhog Day, right? On שבועות, Shavuos, if you see
that it looks like X, the sign is start planting as soon
as שבועות Shavuos is over. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
אמר ליה רב פפא לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Papa le'Rav Ashi,
אנן אדרבי יצחק בר אבדימי מתנינן לה. anan a'de'Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi
masnisan lah. This issue about, about, you know, whether, when to start
planting wheat, we don't teach this in the context of אחיתופל. Achitofel.
We teach
it. Exactly. We teach it in the context of a different statement
of רבי יצחק בר אבדימי. Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi. דאמר רבי יצחק
בר אבדימי, De'amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi, מוצאי יום טוב אחרון של
חג motzei Yom Tov acharon shel Chag
and that basically the point then, it's not about שבועות, Shavuos, it's
about סוכות. Succos. Okay, now part of this question might be or
there's a question about like, well when do you start planting, presumably
you start planting the wheat you plant during the סוכות Succos time,
right, not in שבועות, Shavuos, שבועות Shavuos is when you harvest and
so on, but also when are you
judged, right, on, on סוכות Succos you're judged on water and the
most critical factor in the success of the crops is water. But
you know on שבועות Shavuos you're judged on what? On פירות אילן.
peiros ilan. So it really should have been פסח Pesach where you're
being judged on the wheat. It's a little strange, this שבועות Shavuos
identification. I don't know, I don't know.
You planted it already?
I don't know for when it comes time for planting, you know
four five months from now, four months from now. Anyway, but this
is a more logical thing to link it to סוכות, Succos, A
because of the association with water and B because you're about to
begin planting. So it says like this, מוצאי יום טוב אחרון של
חג הכל צופין לעשן המערכה. motzei Yom Tov acharon shel Chag hakol
tzofin le'ashan ha'ma'arachah.
They're all looking to the smoke that goes up from the, from
the altar in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash from the wood pile
to see where the wind is blowing, right, you know the phrase
where's the wind blowing? נשף כלפי צפון. Nashaf klapei tzafon. And presumably
the determinant is where they see it blow on that last day
of סוכות. Succos. And that's going to determine how it's going to
blow for the rest of the year.
On הושענא רבה. Hoshana Rabbah. Right, so think about הושענא רבה Hoshana
Rabbah as a whole יום הדין. yom ha'din. That's a point identifying
this. Also right the whole idea of the waving of the לולב
lulav is for the רוחות. ruchos. So and you know it's not
just the rain, it's how the wind is going to carry the,
you know, the clouds and so on. But yes, thank you, that's
a good point that's הושענא רבה. Hoshana Rabbah. No, I don't think
so. מוצאי יום טוב אחרון, Motzei Yom Tov acharon, יום טוב Yom
Tov means the שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. No, it means עצרת. Atzeres.
Yeah, שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. Exactly, exactly. It's not הושענא רבה. Hoshana
Rabbah. So you mean שמיני עצרת? Shemini Atzeres?
He knows, good point, and now it's a terrible point.
You had it, הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabbah would be very nice but
it means, but it means שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. Anyway, וכדתני. ve'chid'tani.
Right, exactly. So now you're like the.
Right,
that's when you start saying by the way תפילת גשם Tefillas Geshem
is שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeres, so that definitely makes sense to go
on שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres.
Right. So maybe. Okay.
Right, right, right. Okay.
מוצאי יום טוב אחרון של חג הכל צופין לעשן המערכה. motzei Yom
Tov acharon shel Chag hakol tzofin le'ashan ha'ma'arachah. נשף כלפי צפון. Nashaf
klapei tzafon. If you see it go to the north, then a
south wind is blowing it. Okay, so עניים שמחים ובעלי בתים עצבים.
aniyim smeichim u'va'alei batim atzeivim. So the poor are happy and the
homeowners which are the people that have property are sad because apparently
that means that there's going to be like the right amount of
rain so that there'll be plentiful fruit but not too much so
that it'll actually last. for a long time. So therefore it means
that there's going to be the prices will be low. Okay. Now,
מפני שגשמי שנה מרובים ופירות Mipnei shegishmei shana merubim upeirot oh no,
excuse me, I didn't mean I—the last thing is the next thing.
The opposite. It's going to be plentiful rain, excuse me, ופירות מרקיבים.
upeirot markivim. And because of plentiful rain, the fruits are going to
almost be like overripe and they'll rot soon. So why are the
עניים aniyim happy? Because then they have to get rid of them
fast. The sellers, like the farmers, have to sell them quickly, so
the prices will be low. Okay. So they'll be plentiful and they
will rot quickly, so the prices will be low. Okay. נטה כלפי
דרום, Nata klapei darom, if it's going to be south, so it's
a northern wind, עניים עצבים ובעלי בתים שמחים. Aniyim atzeivim uva'alei batim
smeichim. It's the reverse. מפני שגשמי שנה מועטים, Mipnei shegishmei shana muatim,
a small amount of rain, ופירות משתמרים. upeirot mishtamrim. So they'll be—the
fruit won't be so plentiful, right? It's always a question. Like, that's
not so great for the farmers, but you know, you don't want
there to be too much because then it's like, you know, you
hit that like, you know, that perfect, you know, point. Anyway, so
there won't be an overabundance of fruit so the prices will be
high and they can wait for their price because the fruit will
store. Okay. נטה כלפי מזרח, Nata klapei mizrach, if it's going to
the east, so it's a western wind, הכל שמחים, hakol smeichim, everybody
is happy because that means that apparently the fruit will store, so
the בעלי בתים ba'alei batim are happy, but there'll also be like
an abundance of it, so whatever. It'll be a good, nice balance
between the two.
כלפי מערב, Klapei maarav, to the west, הכל עצבים, hakol atzeivim, everybody
is sad because I guess it means that there'll be few fruit
and they will rot, so nobody's going to benefit from that. All
right. ורמינהי, Ureminhei, anyway, whatever. So a source once. מזרחית עולם יפה.
Mizrachit olam yafeh. It says the east wind is always good. מערבית
עולם קשה. Maaravit olam kasha. The west wind is always bad. And
if you looked at it before, right, we said that the east—what
did we say? We said that when it goes to the—what did
we say? The last one. When it goes to
כלפי
מזרח,
klapei
mizrach, if the smoke is going to the east, everybody is happy,
which means a west wind is the best. And here it says
the reverse, right? The east wind's the best and the west wind
is always bad. Now this goes on. רוח צפונית יפה לחיטין. Ruach
tzafonit yafah lechitin. Okay. בשעה שהביאו שליש. besha'ah shehevi'u shalish. A northern
wind is good to the—to the grain, to the wheat, if it's
already begun to ripen. Okay. וקשה לזיתים בשעה שיניצו, Vekasha lezeitim besha'ah
sheyanitzu, and it's bad for the olives if they've begun to flower.
Okay. ורוח דרומית, Veruach dromit, the southern wind, is קשה לחיטין בשעה
שהביאו שליש kasha lechitin besha'ah shehevi'u shalish is bad for the grain
if it's begun to ripen, ויפה לזיתים
בשעה שיניצו veyafah lezeitim besha'ah sheyanitzu once they've begun to, I think,
flower. Anyway, so—what do you do with the contradiction? Is the east
wind bad or good? The—these ברייתות braitot contradict. And is the west
wind bad or good? They contradict.
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Tanna devei rabi yishmael. Okay, maybe.
ואמר רב יוסף ואיתימא מר זוטרא ואיתימא רב נחמן בר יצחק. Veamar
Rav Yosef ve'itaima Mar Zutra ve'itaima Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. Oh, first
we go to the difference of north and south. וסימנך שולחן בצפון
ומנורה בדרום. Vesimanecha shulchan batzafon umenorah badarom. The שולחן shulchan is in
the north, the שולחן shulchan had bread, that is the wheat, so
the north wind is good for the wheat. And the מנורה menorah
is in the south, that had the oil which is made from
olives, so the south wind is good for the olives. Okay. האי
מרבי דידיה והאי מרבי דידיה. Hai marbi dideih vehai marbi dideih. This
one increases its
own and that—the other—this one increases its own. The northern wind takes
care of, you know, of the מנורה menorah and the southern wind
takes care of the—of the—I got them—the northern wind, excuse me, takes
care of the שולחן shulchan and the southern wind takes care of
the מנורה. menorah. Okay. Anyway, what do you do about the question,
is the east and west wind—you know, which is bad, which is
good? The ברייתות braitot contradict. So lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא
לן והא להו. Ha lan veha lehu. Depends, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
or בבל. Bavel. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot and the רשב״ם Rashbam discuss
why it matters which one is which. Anyway, בבל Bavel was a
much
more—what do you call it?—had much more rain, so, you know, too
much rain would have been a bad thing. Anyway, so it depends
on where you live. I don't know, that's what they say. תניא,
Tanya, I—I can't—whatever. Moving on, moving on. תניא אבא שאול אומר, Tanya
Abba Shaul omer, יום טוב של עצרת ברור סימן יפה לכל השנה
כולה. Yom tov shel atzeret barur siman yafeh lechol hashana kulah. So
now we're not doing it about planting wheat, we're just doing it
more generally. If the שבועות Shavuot is a clear day, it's a
good sign for the whole year. Okay. אמר רב זביד, Amar Rav
Zevid, האי יומא קמא דריש שתא, Hai yoma kama deReish Shata, the
first day of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, interesting, reflecting two days of
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, אי חמים כולי שתא חמים, ei chamim kulei
shata chamim, it's going to be a hot year. רשב״ם Rashbam says
it doesn't mean every day's going to be hot, but, you know,
it'll be a—an—older than—lower than—warmer than average, that's right, year. Okay. אי
קריר כולי שתא קריר. ei karir kulei shata karir. It's going to
be a colder than average year. למאי נפקא מינה? Lemai nafka mina?
What difference does it make? What? Now it could make a difference
for planting, maybe, which is what we've been talking about, but it
says בצלותא דכהן גדול, betzeluta deKohen Gadol, because the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol is going to go into the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So he looks on ראש השנה Rosh Hashana
and he sees what the year's going to be. And then if
he sees it's going to be a hot year, he should pray—pray
maybe for plentiful rains, if it's a cold year he should pray—pray
that—pray for מיתוקא. mituka. So he adjusts his prayer based on what
he's anticipating the year—or he would just pray for—for just a good
year. Yeah, well, okay, that's a good point. But we always have
more כוונה kavanah when we're more concrete. ורבא אמר רב נחמן—okay, Verava
amar Rav Nachman now, that was a big digression. Back to the
point. We had all those פסוקים psukim that were saying
it's דאורייתא, de'oraita, or תוספות Tosafot said, well, not really דאורייתא, de'oraita,
but the גמרא was saying it was דאורייתא. de'oraita. Now we're going
to get those that say no, it's all דרבנן. derabbanan. Okay. ורבא
אמר רב נחמן, Verava amar Rav Nachman, רבא Rava said in the
name of... ורבא אמר רב נחמן. Verava amar Rav Nachman. רבא Rava
says in the name of רב נחמן: Rav Nachman מתנת שכיב מרע
מדרבנן בעלמא היא. matnas shechiv mera miderabanan be'alma hi. It's just דרבנן.
derabanan. שמא תטרוף דעתו. shema titrof da'ato. Lest his mind
get טירוף הדעת, tiruf hadaas, like רש״י, Rashi, get confused. Now the
רשב״ם Rashbam has two very interesting explanations what lest his mind gets
confused means. One means is let if he gets confused then I
mean here he is he's commanding what he wants to have happen.
If we were to demand that it's only binding once they do
a קניין kinyan by the time we get the guy to give
the קניין kinyan he will be not in his right frame of
mind and he won't because as people are getting closer to death
they may lose often lose not always but often they're not in
their right frame of mind and therefore he won't be able to
execute his קניין. kinyan. So he won't be able to do it.
So the רשב״ם Rashbam says okay but like why should we make
an institution just because he won't be able to succeed in doing
what he wants? Like why don't we still stick to our guns?
It's only going to work if you do a קניין. kinyan. Now
he could just say no we see that there is a social
good at letting people try to divest their property in the ways
that they feel they want to do it but anyway but according
to that the reason we did it is because if we demanded
a קניין kinyan he might not be able to get around to
it in time before he loses his clear thinking. The other explanation
which is the much more widely given one which is the second
one in the רשב״ם Rashbam is if we know a concern for
his health. If we were to tell him no we're not concerned
whether he'll be able to divest his property but if we were
to tell him wait no no no this can't happen yet we
need to get a notary and we need to get this and
we need to get that he's going to get so upset
and worked up that it's actually going to hurt his health and
it might actually hasten his death. And therefore we're going to create
this institution because we're very concerned about these things about his state
of mind about his anxiety and health and so on. This actually
is interesting רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein uses this
principle in a number of his medical תשובות tshuvos about
like because in הלכה halacha there's not really much of a basis
for a patient autonomy. The principle is like you're supposed to save
a life and what does it matter what this person wants? Now
maybe there are times where there's a weighing of risks. Should we
do this operation which has so much of a risk and whatever
so there maybe you can find a place where the person should
be able to determine. But in other cases let's say somebody refuses
medication and the doctors are saying like this medication he needs it.
So where is that place in הלכה halacha for patient autonomy if
there's a מצוה mitzva to save a life it shouldn't matter if
the person doesn't want it. So רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein
finds the opening through this principle of שכיב מרע. shchiv mera He
says you try to get some here you're that case you're trying
to force somebody to do something that they don't want to do
force them to take medication here it's even less than this here
it's like he's trying to do something and he's not able to
do it and that we're concerned that that could hasten his death.
So he gets patient autonomy through the back door of פיקוח נפש.
pikuach nefesh. Like if at this period if you don't allow him
a certain degree of self-determination and autonomy and you're frustrating what he
wants to do then it'll actually hasten his death.
That's sort of the opposite though. Here let's say he doesn't want
to take the medication which is going to save him and you're
letting him is he saying that no
רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein is saying you would follow him
and not take the I mean there are some cases he says
no it's so black and white but in
some cases by not taking the medication will hasten his death.
No because רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein says we're going to
give more weight and more concern that his טירוף הדעת tiruf hadaas
will hasten his death more than the not taking of the medication.
Now of course there's some times where clearly so there obviously would
be some exceptions to that. But the point is it's very fascinating
that he uses this as a way to create patient autonomy by
doing it as a hey it'll be פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh here
if we don't give him a certain ability to do what he
wants self-determination at this moment. Okay so the גמרא says like this
ומי אמר רב נחמן הכי? umi amar Rav Nachman hachi? Did רב
נחמן Rav Nachman, really say that? והאמר רב נחמן אף על גב
דאמר שמואל veha'amar Rav Nachman af al gav de'amar Shmuel even though
שמואל Shmuel says המוכר שטר חוב לחבירו וחזר ומחלו מחול ואפילו יורש
מוחל.
hamocher shtar chov lachaveiro vachazar umachalo
machul ve'afilu yoresh mochel. Okay so ראובן Reuven sells owes ראובן Reuven
a thousand dollars. ראובן Reuven sells his שטר shtar to Michael so
now I owe Michael a thousand dollars but the way הלכה halacha
basically conceptualizes this is no I don't really directly owe Michael a
thousand dollars I still owe it to ראובן. Reuven. Michael is just
ראובן's Reuven direct deposit. As soon as the money goes into ראובן's
Reuven account it gets immediately transferred to Michael's. Okay everybody got the
idea? That's how selling a שטר חוב shtar chov works because conceptually
how do you move a debt? It's like if I owe the
money and it's a personal relationship I owe the money to ראובן
Reuven and a debt is an abstract thing how do you move
it that now I owe it to Michael? So what Michael essentially
has done is he's bought the right to collect the debt and
pocket it but still it's owed to ראובן. Reuven. That's how we
conceptualize it. The effect of conceptualizing it like that means that if
ראובן Reuven now says to me I מוחל mochel Dov it would
be a nasty thing to do he sold it to Michael and
then he said forget it you don't have to pay me. I
still owe the money to him and he's still in a position
to waive the debt so Michael now... Now if he's out his
money. Now, now, Michael can go back to ראובן Reuven and collect
for damages. And that's what the רשב"ם says, that's like דיני דגרמי,
dini d'garmi, you sold me something and then you made it worthless,
right, so when you sold it to me it wasn't like an
invalid sale, but after you sold it to me you made it
worthless. So he can go back to ראובן Reuven for damages, but
nevertheless I no longer owe the money to Michael. Okay, so that's
the principle המוכר שטר חובו לחבירו, hamocher shtar chovo l'chavero,
ראובן Reuven sold this debt to Michael, וחזר מחלו, v'chazar mechalo, and
then ראובן Reuven was מוחל mochel it, מחול, machul, it's voided and
I don't owe any money. ואפילו יורש מחל, v'afillu yoresh machal, even
if ראובן Reuven dies and his son inherits the debt, I still
owe the money fundamentally to his son, the son is a continuation
of the father, and the son can be מוחל mochel it and
I would still get out of having to pay Michael. Now, even
though that's שמואל's Shmuel basic principle, okay, what does this have to
do with us? מודה שמואל שאם נתנו במתנת שכיב מרע, modeh Shmuel
she'im netano b'matnat shchiv mera,
if ראובן Reuven gave it to me as a מתנת שכיב מרע,
shchiv mera דאינו יכול למחול, d'eino yachol limchol, then he cannot be
מוחל mochel even while he's still alive and his son can't be
מוחל. mochel. So what does that mean? That means here's the conceptual
point: when he gives it to me as a מתנת שכיב מרע,
shchiv mera even when he's still alive he can't be מוחל. mochel.
Okay, because that's not... when he gives it as a מתנת שכיב
מרע shchiv mera to Michael,
it's now...
no, he didn't give it to you as a מתנת שכיב מרע,
shchiv mera the debt, I owe you the money and then he
was מוחל mochel me. So when he transfers it to Michael, what
it's saying is the מתנת שכיב מרע shchiv mera is more powerful
than a gift than the transferring a debt when you're alive. So
I mean a normal transfer of debt. A normal transfer of debt,
you can't transfer a debt, it's this abstract entity, Michael could just
be the one who collects it. Okay, but a שכיב מרע shchiv
mera we give it so much power that it can actually transfer
the debt. So now when the שכיב מרע does it, I owe
the money directly to Michael and he can't be מוחל. mochel. Now
the גמרא is going to assume if that power would only work
if שכיב מרע were דאורייתא. d'Oraita. What does that have to do
with דאורייתא d'Oraita to דרבנן? d'Rabbanan? The best way to explain it
is the following: if it's דאורייתא, d'Oraita, it's built on what principle?
What were the פסוקים pesukim we quoted before? Not the narrative פסוקים,
pesukim, the הלכה halacha פסוקים pesukim we quoted, והעברתם, right?
So it's based on a principle of ירושה. yerusha. Okay, when a
person dies, when the son inherits, he directly is the... the debt
itself is directly owed to the son. So if שכיב מרע is
based on a דאורייתא d'Oraita principle of ירושה, yerusha, if the שכיב
מרע gives it to Michael, Michael becomes like the שכיב מרע's son
and he directly gets that debt. And since he directly gets that
debt and it's not like through, right, the same way a יורש
yoresh would, then they can't be מוחל. mochel.
Why didn't they
make it כמר יורש k'mar yoresh though, כמר יורש? k'mar yoresh? Okay,
but that's the principle. We're learning from the פסוקים pesukim that there's
a way to do it, it's designed such as to create like
pseudo-ירושה.
yerusha. So Michael is יורש yoresh that debt as far as שכיב
מרע dies. Right, the son of the שכיב מרע cannot be מבטל.
mevatel.
Right, because now the same way if he hadn't done it, I
would have owed it to the son, I owe it directly to
Michael. Okay, so let's take a look. אי אמרת בשלמא דאורייתא, ei
amrat bishlama d'Oraita, if you say it's דאורייתא, d'Oraita, משום הכי אינו
יכול למחול, mishum hachi eino yachol limchol, he can't be מוחל, mochel,
because like I said, then it would work on a principle of
ירושה yerusha and I would owe the money directly to Michael. אלא
אי אמרת דרבנן, ela ei amrat d'Rabbanan, if it's Rabbinic, then presumably
it's the principle of קנין, kinyan, so it shouldn't be different than
if somebody, you know, normally tries to transfer the debt to Michael
where I would still owe it to the first person. אמאי אינו
יכול למחול? amai eino yachol limchol? Why not? So it sounds like
it's really דאורייתא. d'Oraita. So the גמרא says fine, אימא דרבנן ועשוהו
כשל תורה. eima d'Rabbanan v'asu'uhu k'shel Torah. Fine, that doesn't really prove
it. It's Rabbinic, but we're making it as if it's דאורייתא. d'Oraita.
And again, the way I would say it here is we're making
it as if it's a type of a ירושה. yerusha. So this
דין שכיב מרע din shchiv mera might be Rabbinic, but it's Rabbinic
that is given the trappings and the weight and almost the mechanics
of if it were דאורייתא, d'Oraita, and in this case that would
be, if this... going with this explanation, there are other ways of
reading this המוכר שטר חובו, hamocher shtar chovo, but going with this
explanation, it would like making Michael a יורש yoresh and I would
owe that money directly to Michael. Okay, to explain שמואל. Shmuel. We're
just to reconcile שמואל, Shmuel, we have to... oh, within שמואל. Shmuel.
This is an answer within שמואל. Shmuel. Right, however other אמוראים Amoraim
might not hold of it. He might not. Right. רב נחמן, correct.
Correct, right. This is only within שמואל, Shmuel, this is what you
have to say. That is correct. Okay.